<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short report of the honourable iourney into Brabant by his excellencie Graue Mauris, gouernour and Lord Generall of the vnited Netherlandish Prouinces: from the 26. day of Iune, to the 19. day of Iuly, 1602. Together with the taking of Helmont, and of his marching to the strong towne of Graue. Translated out of the Dutch copie printed at Vtricht.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17675</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102846</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838608</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2993</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2993)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1145:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short report of the honourable iourney into Brabant by his excellencie Graue Mauris, gouernour and Lord Generall of the vnited Netherlandish Prouinces: from the 26. day of Iune, to the 19. day of Iuly, 1602. Together with the taking of Helmont, and of his marching to the strong towne of Graue. Translated out of the Dutch copie printed at Vtricht.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. C[reede] for Thomas Pauier, and are to be sold at his shop in Corn-hill neare the exchange, at the signe of the Cat and Parrots,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maurice, --  Prince of Orange, 1567-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2993:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2993:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Short report of the honourable Iourney in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Brabant,</hi> by his Excellencie <hi>Graue Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> Gouernour and Lord Generall of the vnited Netherlandiſh Prouinces: From the 26. day of Iune, to the 19. day of Iuly, 1602.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with the taking of</hi> Helmont, <hi>and of his marching to the ſtrong Towne of</hi> Graue.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Dutch Copie Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Vtricht.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by T. C. for Thomas Pauier, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Corn-hill neare the Exchange, at the Signe of the Cat and Parrots. 1602.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2993:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2993:2"/>
            <head>A SHORT RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Honorable Iourney into <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant,</hi> by his Excellencie <hi>Graue Mauris,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor and Lord Generall of the vnited <hi>Netherlandiſh Prouinces. From the</hi> 26. <hi>day of Iune, to the</hi> 19. <hi>day of Iuly.</hi> 1602.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that his Princely Excellencie, with the honourable Lordes the States, had in the feare of God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded by the moſt commodious and fitteſt meanes to ſuccor and preuent the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and tedious ſiege of <hi>Oſtende,</hi> with intent once wholy to frée the Netherla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſh Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the bloudie yoke of the Tyrannical Spaniards and hipocriticall murtherous Ieſuites, which daily prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe to trouble, not only the welfare of the Netherlandiſh Prouinces, generally, (but alſo to ſuppreſſe and murther all good, godly, bleſſed, and peaceable Kings, Princes, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2993:3"/>
Potentates) that ſo in time they might with more eaſe incorporate the ſaid Netherlandiſh Prouinces. To the end therefore that the ſaid Honourable Lords the States with his princely Excellency, might once wholy ſhake off thoſe common enemies from the neck of thoſe Prouinces generally, and eſtabliſh a firme and an aſſured peace, they haue thought it conuenient to raiſe and bring into the fields a ſtrong and honourable Campe, as well for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> as alſo to deliuer the reſt of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh Prouinces from the yoke of the tyrannous Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards &amp; bloudie Edicts, to which end hath bene aſſembled many outlandiſh ſouldiers, both horſmen &amp; footemen, with great numbers of wagons, as well out of <hi>Brabant</hi> &amp; <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricht,</hi> as from <hi>Holland</hi> and other places, wherof many were couered, and ſome curiouſly painted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Armes of nobles and gentlemen for their eaſe &amp; reſt in the night, which had their <hi>rendes-vous</hi> neare the toll-houſe beyond <hi>Nimmeghen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when the greateſt number were aſſembled at the ſaid place, they attended his Excellencies comming, who departed from the <hi>Grauen-baeghe</hi> the eight day of Iune in the morning, to take muſter of his Royal Camp, which he accompliſhed vpon the <hi>Eltenberge</hi> heath, and (finding the ſame to be betwéene <hi>5.</hi> and <hi>6.</hi> thouſand horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>28.</hi> thouſand footemen, and neare about <hi>4.</hi> thouſand wagons, well, and in good order mounted and furniſhed) he with the honourable Lords the States, paſſed through the whole army, demanding as well of the Cauallery, as of the <hi>Infantery,</hi> if there were any one amongſt them that found himſelfe agréeued with the pay of the States, and if any ſuch were, they ſhould ſpeake: but none hauing cauſe to complaine, they demaunded farther, if they were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2993:3"/>
reſolued to hazard their liues with them in this moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable action, to the glorie of God, and welfare of their father Land, wherevnto the ſouldiers generally applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, deſiring nothing more then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might be brought to the ſight of their enemies, againſt whom they might with their weapons, rather then with words, ſhew how greatly they were affected to manifeſt their courages, and once again to driue thoſe common enemies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome out of the fields, and to make them run before them as ſhéepe.</p>
            <p>Herevpon his Excellency cauſed certaine bridges to be laid ouer the Maze, and the 26. day of Iune began to ſet forward in ſo good order, that it ſéemed no leſſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, then pleaſant and glorious to behold ſo rare an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the honorable Lords the States, marching in moſt warlike order, and diuided into thrée troupes or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, euery one flancked with wagons for their defence as they marched, with many field péeces, and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries therevnto belonging: The firſt troupe or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was ledde by his Excellencie: The ſecond by <hi>Graue William,</hi> and the third by <hi>Graue Eruſt</hi> or <hi>Erneſtus,</hi> in very good order: Notwithſtanding the miſdemeanour of ſome ſelfe-willed ſouldiers, as in the beginning appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by one, who forced a woman, and was therefore preſently hanged. After that two Scottiſh ſouldiers fel together by the eares, the one (hauing wounded the other to the death) were forthwith by Martiall diſcipline har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebuſhed.</p>
            <p>Thus kéeping their courſe along by the ſide of the Maze, on the left hande of the ſaide Riuer by <hi>Venlo, Ruremonde,</hi> and other places neare about <hi>Maſtricke,</hi> they lay ſtill fiue dayes, furniſhing themſelues with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2993:4"/>
Béere, Bread, and other victualls, for they had brought with them many Ouens to bake their Bread. After ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient prouiſion made, they marched forward towards <hi>Tongheren,</hi> and ſo vpwards to <hi>Truyen,</hi> within ſome halfe league of <hi>Lew,</hi> forcing all the Villages thereabouts to bring in their contributions, which amounted to an incredible ſumme of money.</p>
            <p>As they lay quietly at this place, it happened that ſome of our ſouldiers raunged a little too farre, and were by the Moores entrapped and ſlaine. In reuenge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of certaine Horſemen were ſent out, who not forgetting their arrant, ſlew diuers Moores, and Horſemen, and brought with them to the Campe, eightéene Horſemen priſoners, and two gray Friars.</p>
            <p>After that his Princely Excellency had remayned at this place a fewe dayes, and put his people into Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile order, hée ſent a Trumpetter vnto the Admirall of <hi>Arragon,</hi> Generall for the Archduke (who had intren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched himſelfe verie ſtrongly neare vnto the Towne of <hi>Tien</hi>) ſignifying vnto him, that he was now readie to giue him Battaile, and that therefore hée ſhould now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his proud words héeretofore vttered when he was priſoner if he had the courage. But he anſwered he had no Commiſſion from the Archduke to fight, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued his honour and reputation as he thought.</p>
            <p>After this, his Excellencie as a valiant Prince mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched towards the enemy with certaine horſe and foote, euen to his Trenches, but the enemy kept himſelfe cloſe. His Excellencie perceiuing that the Admirall durſt not ſhewe himſelfe in the field notwithſtanding that he was come ſo farre to ſéeke him, he ſuddainly turned backe, and comming neare vnto <hi>Helmont,</hi> ſummoned the ſame,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2993:4"/>
but after refuſall made, his Excellencie planted ſixe péeces of Ordenance againſt the walles, and after ſome ſhot made, at the laſt vpon the <hi>18.</hi> day of this Moneth of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they yéelded the Towne, and then his Excellencie marched to the Towne of <hi>Graue,</hi> enuironed and beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſame, and tooke the Caſtle of <hi>Batenborgh,</hi> which ſtandeth on the other ſide of the <hi>Maze.</hi> Our people doo fortifie <hi>Helmont</hi> and <hi>Eyndouen,</hi> ſeruing as Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes or Forts vnto our Campe.</p>
            <p>The euerliuing, Almightie, and potentiall God, vouchſafe to bleſſe and kéepe his Excellencie, and to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all his godly procéedings: and graunt happie &amp; proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous effect to his attempts, for the general peace and quietnes of all the Lowe Countries. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching <hi>Oſtend,</hi> the Towne is (God be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) in very good tearmes, although many of late haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſicknes, which lately is ceaſed, and the enemy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth his ſiege, though more coldly then heretofore, and his Forces without the Town is not aboue <hi>3000.</hi> men, and the ſame ſo vexed with ſickneſſe and the plague, that many die daily. They haue no want in the Towne, for although the enemy practiſeth daily whatſoeuer meanes mans braine is able to inuent, to reſtraine the comming in of ſhippes, with men, munition, and other prouiſions neceſſary, yet God and the ſeas doo ſo fruſtrate their deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, that the enemie without all doubt remaineth void of all hope by any force to winne the ſame: But if any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the reaſon why he then ſo obſtinately continueth his ſiege, the reaſon is the haughtineſſe of his mind, aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that it ſhould be publiſhed to the worlde, that the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2993:5"/>
States ſhould be able to defend ſo baggage a Towne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all his forces, and to make good the defence thereof againſt ſo many his policies, practiſes, and deuiſes, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſame in time to come, might redound to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall diſgrace, and contrariwiſe incourage and animate the States his enemies, as well as other Princes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe his Forces, and conteme the valour of his Italians and Spaniards, on whoſe vertue &amp; manhood, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke ſo much ſtandeth (as his predeceſſors, and other Spaniſh Gouernors haue done before him) that he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no Nation comparable vnto them, nor able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with them in martiall affaires, not calling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance how often they haue bene foyled, and put to the worſt, ſince theſe warres firſt beganne, both by Sea and Lande, not onely by the natiue people of the Lowe Countries, but alſo by forraine Souldiers of ſundrie Nations. It is not then greatly to bee maruelled at, that the Archduke continueth his ſiege before <hi>Oſtende,</hi> (though more coldly and ſparingly then at the firſt, as is before ſaide) ſéeing he léedeth himſelfe with two vaine expectations, for (ſaith hée) <hi>Omne tempus habet,</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that the States wearie of ſo infinite a charge, may in time forget to ſupply ſhe wants of the Towne, or elſe that it may ſo fall out, that with Spaniſh Piſtolets, hée may corrupt ſome ſuch in the Towne, that he may at laſt attaine to his wiſhed deſire: for without all doubt, he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath, nor can haue any other hope to obtaine the Towne, although he lie before it theſe ſeuen yeares, for all ſuch as come out of <hi>Brabant</hi> or <hi>Flaunders,</hi> confirme this to be moſt true, and to be the opinion of the Duke himſelfe, and of all his Spaniards and Spaniſh affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2993:5"/>God graunt they may neuer haue better hope in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their bloudie attempts. But if any will héere ſay that there remaineth yet an other hope to the Archduke, namely that the Sea may waſte and eate vp the towne, ſo as the States Forces may be forced to abandon the ſame, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay, but if it ſo pleaſe God, both the Towne and all the Countrey may be ſwallowed vp with the ſea, but if the olde Towne be in ſome daunger, yet the new Towne is not ſo: but if both ſhould happen to be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, no doubt the States are ſo prouident of their defence and maintenance of their Trade (which otherwiſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt woulde be greatly hindered, by Gallyes and other ſhipping which might there haue conuenient harbour) that they would there builde ſome conuenient Forte, which ſhould no leſſe annoy the enemie then the Towne of <hi>Oſtend</hi> it ſelfe doeth or hath done, for the kéeping of that place dooth moſt highly concerne all <hi>Hollande</hi> and <hi>Zealande,</hi> and all other Nations which are accuſtomed to trafficque too and from thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
            <p>It is written from <hi>Rome,</hi> to be moſt certaine, that vpon Wedneſday laſt being the 20. day of this Moneth of Iuly, the Marſhall <hi>Byron</hi> was beheaded at <hi>Paris,</hi> not openly, but in the Tower there, called the <hi>Baſtill,</hi> God graunt all Traytors may receiue the like reward. It is ſaid that very many great perſonages are of his conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, what wil follow, time wil ſhewe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2993:6"/>
            <head>The Copie of a Letter ſent from Middlebrough by Mai. E. D. to his friend in London.</head>
            <p>WHerein is ſhewed, that ſince the 19. day of Iuly, 1602. his Excellencie continuing his ſiege before the Towne of <hi>Graue,</hi> tooke a Forte made ouer the Riuer <hi>Moſa,</hi> and from thence battered the Towne where it is weakeſt, hée is in great hope and likelihood to winne it ſhortly, being not eaſie to be reſcued: But at the other ſide of the <hi>Moſa,</hi> which without ſome fight is not eaſily to be done. We heare the Admirall hath ſent ſupply towards <hi>Flanders,</hi> fearing ſome attempt by an other way thereabout. And about <hi>Turnhout</hi> likewiſe the enemy made ſome aſſembly, and about <hi>Venlo.</hi> The Prince <hi>Mauris</hi> iſſued in great haſte foorth of his Campe, with ſome ten thouſand footemen, and foure thouſand Horſe, making towards them, what ſucceſſe will happen we ſhall ſhortly know. There are as it is reported, ſome two thouſand men in <hi>Graue,</hi> the Princes Horſemen raunge about <hi>Hertigenboſche,</hi> ſo that it is like halfe beſieged lacking neceſſaries: And <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant</hi> is cleane eaten vp as well of the Spaniſh as of our ſouldiers, but by meanes of the Riuer <hi>Moſa</hi> our Campe lacketh nothing. Many other places be taken here and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2993:6"/>
there of no great moment. We heare here little of the Archduke. The Counſell of States generall are gone toward the Camp: Some negociation vnderhand is ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, which time will bring to light. There is good order and diſcipline kept all about.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Oſtend</hi> we heare nothing but good: For the great huge Fagots filled with ſtones, called Puddings or Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciges to be rolled, cannot be ſtirred, and they haue cut them in two, but it will not be of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they muſt begin ſome other inuention.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
